<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>memory management on Ante</title>
    <link>https://antelang.org/categories/memory-management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in memory management on Ante</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://antelang.org/categories/memory-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stable, Mutable References</title>
      <link>https://antelang.org/blog/stable_mutable_refs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://antelang.org/blog/stable_mutable_refs/</guid>
      <description>Introduction  In my first blog post I introduced &amp;amp;shared mut references as a way to achieve safe, shared mutability in a language with unboxed types. For more information on those, start with the first blog post. As a brief summary though, &amp;amp;shared mut references can be aliased freely and mutate freely with the one restriction of not being able to be projected into any &amp;ldquo;shape-unstable&amp;rdquo; types.
What is a shape-unstable type?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplification Through Addition</title>
      <link>https://antelang.org/blog/simplification_through_addition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://antelang.org/blog/simplification_through_addition/</guid>
      <description>Ante&amp;rsquo;s goal was always to be a slightly higher level language than Rust. I always imagined Ante to fill this gap in language design between higher-level garbage collected languages like Java, Python, and Haskell, and lower level non-garbage collected languages like C, C++, and Rust. I still think there&amp;rsquo;s room there for a language which tries to manage things by default but also allows users to manually do so if needed as an optimization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Effects, Ownership, and Borrowing</title>
      <link>https://antelang.org/blog/effects_ownership_and_borrowing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://antelang.org/blog/effects_ownership_and_borrowing/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Algebraic Effects are a useful abstraction for reasoning about effectful programs by letting us leave the interpretation of these effects to callers. However, most existing literature discusses these in the context of a pure functional language with pervasive sharing of values. What restrictions would we need to introduce algebraic effects into a language with ownership and borrowing - particularly Ante?1
 Ownership Consider the following program:
effect Read a with read : Unit -&amp;gt; a the_value (value: a) (f: Unit -&amp;gt; b can Read a) : b = handle f () | read () -&amp;gt; resume value This seems like it&amp;rsquo;d pass type checking at first glance, but we can easily construct a program that tries to use the same moved value twice:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Achieving Safe, Aliasable Mutability with Unboxed Types</title>
      <link>https://antelang.org/blog/safe_shared_mutability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://antelang.org/blog/safe_shared_mutability/</guid>
      <description>This is part of Ante&amp;rsquo;s goal to loosen restrictions on low-level programming while remaining fast, memory-safe, and thread-safe.
 Background  When writing low-level, memory-safe, and thread-safe programs, a nice feature that lets us achieve all of these is an ownership model. Ownership models have been used by quite a few languages, but the language which popularized them was Rust. In Rust, the compiler will check our code to ensure we have no dangling references and cannot access already-freed memory (among other errors).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
